Hey everyone, in this video I'll be
giving you the ultimate beginners guide
to Referens Crawlers, the turbo wild card
to Referensspelet, the turbo wild card
from Referens Survivors. This game is
from Referensserien. This game is
incredible and there's some strategies
to make the beginning of the game a lot
easier which will be covered in this
video as well as going over just the
general flow of the game as there's a
lot of things to do as you progress your
way through it. I'll also be covering
the best crawlers and there is a clear
winner right now which we'll be getting
into as well as some very powerful
combinations that I'll be touching on.
Now one thing I really want to touch on
first is the combos in this game with
the pancakes you get in the tutorial.
It's the major way to succeed in this
game. So essentially we want to start
with cards that have a zero cost,
progress to the cards of the one cost as
you can see their effects have doubled
and this gets really crazy when you go
into a flow of multiple different cards
and get a bunch of different relics
later on. So you always want to be going
for this strategy. Now if you have three
mana and you got a card with one and one
two, you can actually start with the
card with one and progress to the second
card and get a big boost to your damage.
And there's also some very powerful
crawler cards which are like the
characters in this game which give you
mana allowing you to flow between
multiple cards doing some pretty crazy
amounts of damage. So go over cards
first and the blacksmith which you
likely don't have unlocked at the start
of the game you will at a certain point
is very useful cuz this lets us put more
relics onto these. But some of the first
kill skill cards that you're looking for
especially early on the whip is decent.
It's going to attack every enemy. You
typically want to open with that as it
can take out enemies and then you can
flow into your other cards with. And
things like the King Bible are very
useful early on as it's about reducing
the damage you take and the King Bible
comes with knockback. The knife is okay
being able to crit can take out a lot of
enemies quickly but depending on the
character you're playing some do prefer
to go with like the magic wand over the
knife but we'll cover that when we go
over the different characters or
crawlers in this game. Some other very
powerful cards like the Gatti Amari
Amari here and Puma Rolla. This is a
card you definitely want to get early on
as possible because this is going to
give you some health regeneration
allowing you to sustain yourself. So the
zero cost cards some characters will
benefit a lot from the whip being able
to damage multiple enemies and do a flat
out eight damage to them. The knife will
hit multiple targets as well but it'll
do a total of 40 damage with the
potential to crit. Magic wands are
really good on a certain character and
they'll always go after a certain
target. This is really good if you
increase the amount of projectiles that
you can create cuz this will outscale
the others in damage. Some other early
on cards are armored. This one is a
little tricky but it's obviously meant
to set up and combo into some of the
higher level cards. And as mentioned the
King Bible's one of the better cards in
the early game because it's got a one
cost here it can get doubled up to 80
damage and has a chance to knockback
which is extremely useful. Sometimes you
can find a different cards here like
this one increases the mana cost which
can be nice if you want to combo. And
you'll also find things like the hollow
hearts here which can give you
additional health. This is good if you
don't want to flow through your deck as
much as you can also go and skip or
banish cards as well. Certain characters
going to want to do that differently.
But early on typically you're going to
want to take the hollow hearts just to
give yourself some more survivability
and go for things like the King Bible.
Typically when you're looking to pick
cards you want to find what you need for
your deck. You want to have the most
zero to one cost cards a little bit less
for two and obviously a lot less for
three just so you're able to flow
through them in your deck a little
quicker. And in addition to this you can
combine cards to get a very powerful
powerful effect out of them which is
sometimes difficult to use like some of
them have a very high cost of three for
the damage they put out. Not super good
unless you got a lot of cards that are
going to give yourself more mana. And
for card upgrades to the blacksmith
typically we want to go with our ones
that we're cycling through often cuz you
can get things that give you additional
projectiles. Having that on your knife
is really nice when you're using it very
often. So these are typically the ones
you want to boost up to the second relic
slot as soon as possible and then
proceed to one specific to your build
like the guns. Now for our characters
early on Imelda is extremely powerful.
Each of them has different abilities so
you have one ability when the character
is played this will give you 15
experience and when you play a yellow
card you're going to get one experience
percentage growth per card. So this can
scale up pretty quickly. Certain
characters will have different benefits
here and they also come with different
stats like for example this one here
comes with an additional mana and
additional XP growth whereas a character
like Pugnala here gets an additional 30
percentage might and extra two in her
hand. There's also some other characters
that get some pretty crazy buffs like
Giovanna here getting a hand of mana and
50% luck greed and re-five rerolls. And
each character is going to come with
their own type of weapons that they're
going to start off with like Imelda for
example comes with the magic wands and
her whole kit is around getting
increased projectiles so when you use
your magic wands they do insane amounts
of damage. Pasqualina is also really
good one here gets additional 10 area
which does damage to multiple targets in
an area of effect whenever this card is
played and it increases your hand by one
when a purple card is played. Pasqualina
actually has some pretty great synergy
with Arca here which gains one mana when
a purple card is played. So these two
can actually go together well because
you're able to use two of the crawlers
and eventually three of them as you can
see here so you can actually combine
them together, use their benefits cuz
getting mana back on purple cards is
really nice. You get both of these
flowing at the same time you can get
some infinite combos going. We have
Antonio and Gennaro here who get
benefits from red cards which are some
of the more common damage ones. This
will deal 60 damage when a red card is
played. This increases your damage by
10% although I do find them to be a
little bit weaker than other characters
in this game. There is an overwhelming
number of targets that get benefits from
purple cards like Pasqualina, Arca here,
Giovanna. We also have benefits from
Dommario and the only blue card benefits
from Poe here which draws one card when
a blue card is played which are not very
common. But Poe does start off with the
garlic cards which are very strong.
Honestly the strongest character right
now is Pugnala as mentioned she can be
crazy. She also starts off with her gun
cards. Whenever you play the Pugnala
card you get an additional 20% damage
and you draw one card when a yellow card
is played. This gets pretty crazy due to
how many yellow cards are in the game
and her pistols are just so powerful. So
yeah she is probably the strongest. I'd
also say Imelda is really good early on
too. The magic wands are getting your
extra projectiles up is very useful.
Pasqualina can also be a great choice
too. And I've also had a lot of luck
with Giovanna here getting 20 luck when
Giovanna is played and you draw one card
when a purple card is played. So you can
get some crazy combos going with
Giovanna and Arca as well as I mentioned
similar to Pasqualina and Arca. So
depends on who you like to play. I'd
recommend trying out all the different
characters. I've had again most success
with Pugnala and Imelda here but you can
get some great success with all the
characters depending on your RNG for
your rolls. It's just that Pugnala is
typically going to have an easier time
with that. And there are other
characters that you can unlock and just
depends where you're at in the
progression but you're going to get
these ones are very early on so they're
going to be ones you want to get good
with as they have some very useful kits.
My personal preference right now is
rolling with Pugnala here and then
having Arca as the backup for the
additional three mana when his card is
played and adding mana when you play
purple cards which really does work well
since Pugnala actually starts off with
an extra purple card too. Now this takes
us to the shop. There's some very
powerful abilities that you can get here
and I'll just refund this here so you
get an idea of what you should be
working your way towards. One of the
most impactful is actually greed. This
will give you more coins per rank. You
want to get this up to two points as
quickly as possible cuz 50% more gold is
very useful when it's such a valuable
resource that we're using so often. I
you also won't have all of these
unlocked at the start of the game and
you'll unlock more as you proceed
through but it's also a nice idea to
take at least one point into growth here
being able to get additional XP just
means you're leveling up and getting
further in your runs. You might think
max health is nice and it can be a good
choice but I typically like to go with a
bit of might here. 20% more damage is
actually a massive boost here. Whenever
you unlock recovery getting one health
point per rank after each encounter is
also extremely useful. I'd recommend
grabbing these here early as possible as
well as throwing on a reroll. This is
nice to at least take one point into
just so that you can choose different
options. This is actually one of the
more impactful ones. You may even want
to take a couple points into it. And as
you continue to level up you get things
like the hand here and then the amount.
Amount is one of the most broken things
in this game. Being able to fire another
projectile in certain weapons is crazy.
So that's one that we like to have just
for that extra at will or basically when
you start the game you get that
additional projectile to shoot. Banish
is another good one when you unlock it
cuz you can remove two cards and when
you get into the flow of the game
sometimes you don't want specific cards
to show up for your build so this can
work very well giving you a bit more
choice over your own destiny. I also
like to take the skip card which can
give you experience instead. Sometimes
you don't want to grab a card like if
you're playing Pugnala sometimes you
want to flow through your deck quicker
so that you can use your relics that you
have built into your cards. So sometimes
it's better just to not take it and even
if you can get XP out of it that's
great. Reroll it a few times see if you
get a card that works with your build.
If you don't you can always just skip it
and get some XP or even banish the
cards. Now there's also things like the
crawler slot. This is the one that you
definitely want to grab as soon as you
unlock it. Getting two crawlers is
really good when they have such powerful
effects on their cards. Same thing with
cool down getting an additional mana
point is insanely impactful so that
you're able to cast more spells in
combat. At this point I'd probably
recommend taking another point in might.
Getting an extra 40% damage is pretty
crazy for the cost that it has. And
honestly taking another point in growth
is not a bad idea. I like to get this up
to like if you can swing it the three
upgrades in the greed for an additional
gold is really good. Area can be nice
for just a bit of splash damage to take
out enemies with the lower cost. I
wouldn't recommend going any higher than
that. And revival once you unlock this
for 4,000 gold you get a chance revive
once per rank which is really nice. And
after that we'll take a point into the
hand. It's nice to have a good flow of
all of these. Luck can also be an
impactful thing to have. Magnet will
give you additional draw effects which
is actually really good too. I should
have mentioned that a little sooner. You
want to be drawing as many cards more
options you have with a lot of these
rogue like deck builders the better.
Sometimes you just have something that
fits into your build a little bit better
so this is one we want to grab. And
we'll put a couple points into the max
health just so that we're a little bit
more survivable. There's also the curse
here. This is something you can when you
get better at the game increasing the
enemy strength but you'll get additional
XP. It is challenging but it's worth it
if you are good with the game and the
mechanics once you get grasp on it. Also
duration is pretty impactful. This
allows your duration your uh
cards to last longer. Eventually, you'll
get a lot of relics that can make it so
they basically last the entire combat,
so you don't have to worry too, too
much. You can take a couple points into
that. And now for the actual game
itself, you're going to get a bunch of
different unlocks. They're going to show
you things like the lamps. You always
want to be busting these down. Whenever
you see a lamp like that, always run
into it here. And anytime you see really
anything, those are priority, just so
that you can get maybe an item or a
different thing that's going to help out
with your build. Now, I'm playing as
Pugnala right now, which if I play her
card, I would get additional 20% damage.
It's a crawler card, so it will stay and
give us extra benefits here. And this
can be really impactful, cuz you'll draw
two cards when your card is played. So,
I would like to go with a flow of going
into her into the spellbinder, but you
can also use this to get the 40% damage.
We always want to pancake at 0123, so
Pugnala, and then flowing into the Aid
the Sparrow. This is going to take out
all those enemies there, as you can see.
It does 672 damage right at the start.
It is pretty insane how overpowered she
is. That took them all out. If I had any
I would have been able to put on the
pistols there. And with her current
build, she has high-cost cards at the
start, so I'm going to look for the
lower-cost ones. But if you're playing
as someone like Impala or the mage girl
there, you may want to take some of the
higher-cost cards, cuz she's got a lot
of low-cost ones. You you always want to
fill it out, so your deck is like
obviously low-cost heavy, but you just
want to be able to flow through it and
get the combos a little easier. So, this
a knife is not amazing, but we're going
to take it here, as this does give us a
bit of extra damage. Now, here I didn't
get anything super lovely, so I can
reroll it here to get something new. Got
a might card, that's pretty nice. Puma
Rola is also very effective, getting
that one heal, super useful to have. I'm
going to go with the might here, cuz
she's really good with boosting up her
damage. I'm putting it on the knife
here, cuz we're going to start off with
this. Being able to boost up your damage
and then play another card that's going
to be boosted is really effective, so we
can go ahead there. And unfortunately, I
don't have any more mana. And onto our
second turn here. Spellbinder won't
really be super impactful. This will get
us two cards.
But we could also go with a knife here.
For these zero-cost cards, sometimes
it's nice just so that you can, you
know, see we drew two cards, and I can
play another spellbinder, cuz it's free.
Then they'll draw another card. I can
play another spellbinder here. And the
cards starting to break. Got to watch
out. If you continually keep playing
cards, this can have consequences. So,
we're pretty early on, so that wasn't
really like the most optimal way to do
it, but we can always flow into our next
cards here, or I can play the knife card
to get the boost of the damage, flow
into the light tome here to get
additional mana, to then be able to cast
the Aid the Sparrow. And if these
enemies were still standing, we could
use our even more powerful gun shot
here. Now, I don't have anything with
knockback, so I am going to take the
King Bible here. I could have also
rerolled that, just to look a little bit
further into it here. And we got
ourselves an area card, amazing. Always
be breaking those apart. And we got
another nice situation, where I can go
into spellbinder here, which again, it's
just going to keep recalling, cuz I
don't have any more cards, but I can
then use the knife there, getting that
damage boost, flowing into the
light tome. Going with King Bible would
be nice if there's enemies I need to
push back, if I needed the damage, but
adding four mana is really nice, when I
can use Aid the Sparrow here, and then I
have four mana to then blast away with
the final weapon there. So, that's kind
of the flow to Pugnala. You want to get
your mana regeneration up. We got our
Puma Rola here now, which is great. Now,
we got health regeneration, mana
regeneration, and it's just the start of
the fight. So, yeah. Honestly, throwing
on Puma Rola is really good, cuz we got
pretty much everything we need now, so
we can flow into the knife here. I am
going to grab the light tome. This is
just a great combo here in early for
Pugnala, and then blowing away with her
three-cost revolver. Having low amounts
of cards is really nice here, and that's
why skipping is is totally fine in
rerolling at times. Here, I might just
grab the empty tome, or go for a reroll,
see what we got. Another light tome's
not a bad idea with how impactful it is
for our gun, so we're going to roll with
that there. But again, you don't always
want to be taking too many of these
abilities. Go after the question marks,
too. Sometimes there's really good
effects here. I'm going to do the same
flow that I did here into Aid the
Sparrow, and then finish them off with
the pistol there. Very impactful, as you
see. Another not so great. I'm going to
go with the reroll, hope for better.
Nothing really great here. You can
banish cards, like let's say if you
didn't want to have the golden armor
here, you can just banish a card and
continue on. And here we got an evolve
card. Sometimes these are worth doing,
if you need more cards with a higher
cost. I don't need a two-cost card, so
we can just leave this here and not take
it. And here we're taking on a boss.
Now, funny enough, I don't have my
three-cost card, so I'm going to use
spellbinder and hope Yeah, we got it,
perfect. So, now it's actually properly
drawing the two cards. We were only able
to draw one prior to this. This is
great, cuz then we can flow from our
light tome here to the one-cost card.
This gives us two additional mana, or
four total mana. We can go into Aid the
Sparrow, and then use use our gun again.
Crazy combos there, and then we can flow
into knife, resetting our cost here. We
do have another card. Nothing super
amazing. You could go with the stone
mask, that's nice, just cuz it's a card
that's going to destroy itself.
Typically, I like to take any of these
cards that are like a free cost, so I
can go boom here, and then scale up to
20%, then the card is destroyed. And
unfortunately, that does restart our
combo, but I actually don't have any two
costs that I can use. I only have one
mana. So, we're going to use spellbinder
and hope that we're able to select
something that works. We got light tome,
that gives us four mana. Only have four
Yeah, this ends up working out in our
favor. And we have two mana left, so I
could use the light tome here, and then
flow into the gun, which is not ideal,
but we'll flow through our deck quick
enough. And again, another great combo
here. If I had more damage, I could go
with this, but I'm going to draw cards,
cuz yeah, I want to get that one in my
hands. Go with the light tome again, Aid
the Sparrow, and finish off with the
pistol. That is crazy, and that's why
Pugnala is one of the strongest
characters in this game. Even crazier,
when you can reduce the mana cost. If
you get another card, I wouldn't
recommend using it on your pistol, but
if you get another three-cost card, you
can actually bring it down to two, and
that can be crazy. Or you can even use
the light tome and give the two mana
head a zero mana cost. So, some pretty
crazy combinations. Even like a King
Bible with only a zero cost, pretty good
way to open up with a weak pushback type
attack. And typically, yeah, we want to
have that Puma Rola there, getting
ourselves some health regeneration. Just
lets us go through and keep our health
maximized. So, that is a beginner's
guide to Referens Crawlers. Let me know
guide to Referensspelet. Let me know
if you'd like to see more content
regarding this game. I had a lot of fun
with it, honestly. It's a really great
game. And lots of great deck builders
have been releasing this year. So, hit
the subscribe button below if you
enjoyed this video, and we'll catch
y'all in the next one.